{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in\nbiology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (pr. LAY-ven-hoke). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the\n\"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10\npoints, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.",
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's visit to the Keeling Islands inspired his book The Structure and Distribution of\nCoral Reefs. As part of that same trip with Robert FitzRoy, he noticed that different finches on\nthe Galapagos Islands occupied different niches. For 10 points, name this man whose time on the\nBeagle inspired him to introduce the theory of evolution by natural selection.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles Darwin",
        "Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker’s work The Sand Reckoner is the most comprehensive surviving source for Aristarchus’\nheliocentric theory. He was the first to develop formulas for the volume and surface area of a sphere and\ninvented a namesake “screw” used for raising water, but his “death ray” did not actually sink a fleet\nattacking his home, Syracuse. For ten points, name this scientist who supposedly ran through the streets\nshouting “Eureka!” after discovering the principle of buoyancy.",
      "answer": [
        "Archimedes of Syracuse",
        "Archimedes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist beat Emile Berliner to the patent of the carbon transmitter and is attributed with\ncreating the world’s first industrial research and development lab, found in West Orange, New Jersey. The\nquote “genius is 1 percent inspiration and 99 percent perspiration” is attributed to this Wizard of Menlo\nPark. For ten points, name this prolific inventor of the phonograph, movie camera, and incandescent light\nbulb.",
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Edison",
        "Edison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Daniel Dennett wrote a book titled for this man’s “Dangerous Idea.” Some of this man’s work was jointly published with Alfred Russel Wallace. His work was defended by the “Bulldog” Thomas Huxley as superior to the similar theories proposed by Lamarck. This man described his journey to the Galapagos Islands in 1839’s The Voyage of the Beagle. For ten points, name this British scientist whose On the Origin of Species is considered the cornerstone of evolutionary biology.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles Darwin",
        "Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man stuck a needle in his own eye during his studies on light and color, which he published in\nOpticks. This man feuded with Gottfried Leibniz over credit for the invention of calculus, a system of\nmath that inspired, but was not proven in, this man’s Principia Mathematica. For ten points, name this\nEnglish scientist who developed the law of universal gravitation and the three laws of motion.",
      "answer": [
        "Sir Isaac Newton",
        "Newton",
        "Isaac Newton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick the Great gave this man the nickname “Cyclops,” in reference to his worsening vision in one eye; later, this man remarked “Now I will have fewer distractions,” upon losing sight in both eyes. The publication of this man’s Letters to a German Princess was supported by Catherine the Great. This thinker developed basic graph theory to conclude that no path could cross each of the seven bridges of Konigsberg only once. For ten points, name this Swiss mathematician, the namesake of the constant e.",
      "answer": "Leonhard Euler , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man declared he would not sacrifice “a frog’s hind legs” for the social experiment that his home country was conducting. The Institute of Experimental Medicine’s Physiology wing was first headed by this man, who studied transmarginal inhibition, an organism’s response to stress. He implanted permanent fistulas in test subjects to measure saliva levels, laying the groundwork for his research in classical conditioning. For ten points, name this Russian psychologist who probably did not ring an actual bell to make his dogs drool.",
      "answer": "Ivan Pavlov"
    },
    {
      "question": "When observing Saturn, this scientist claimed to see two “ears” that were later shown to be its rings. This author of Two New Sciences and Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems discovered the phases of Venus and the four largest moons of Jupiter, a set that he now names. For ten points, name this Italian scientist who was put under house arrest by the Roman Inquisition for professing the Copernican heliocentric theory.",
      "answer": [
        "Galileo Galilei",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s willingness to testify as a character witness convinced a judge to drop an anti-Communist trial against W.E.B. Du Bois. This scientist’s namesake field equations can be used to calculate spacetime geometry and includes the cosmological constant, which is referred to as this scientist’s “biggest blunder.” In1952,thisscientistwasofferedthepresidencyofIsrael.Fortenpoints,namethisscientistwhodeveloped the theory of relativity and the equation E equals m c squared.",
      "answer": "Albert Einstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man created a \"Spirit Thermometer\" filled with liquor to be displayed in the courtofhispatron,FerdinandoIIdeMedici.PopeUrbanVIII's[[theeighth's]]inquisitorsled an investigation against this man after he published “Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems.” A legends tells how this man dropped two balls of different massesoffthe Leaning Tower to test an Aristotelian hypothesis. Four moons of Jupiter are named for, for ten points, which Italian physicist and astronomer? ANSWER:GalileoGalilei(orGalileodi Vincenzo Bonaiutide'Galilei; accept either underlined portion) 2021-22 C Set History (9) Following his return from exile, this monarch formally abandoned the institutionof slavery in 1942 in an effort to finish the reforms of Yohannes IV.Thisman,whobannedthe Oromo language, was removed by the communist Derg regime. This negus [[NEH-gus]] failed to resist an Italian invasion in the 1930s, leading to his nation'soccupation.Thefinal emperor of Ethiopia was, for ten points, what monarch, sometimes known asRasTafari?",
      "answer": [
        "HaileSelassieI",
        "RasTafaribefore mentioned",
        "LijTafari Makonnen before \"Tafari\"",
        "Lij Tafari before \"Tafari\"",
        "Lij TafariMakonnen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Thisalchemistandpursuerofthephilosopher'sstonedevelopedatheoryofcolorhe discussed in the book Opticks. This scientist's MathematicalPrinciplesofNaturalPhilosophy explained his law of universal gravitation, developed using a calculus notation he derived independently of Gottfried Leibniz [[LIBE-nitz]]. Fortenpoints,namethisEnglishpolymath who also theorized three eponymous laws of motion.",
      "answer": "Sir IsaacNewton"
    },
    {
      "question": "An injury kept this academic from representing the UK at the 1948 Olympics as a marathon runner. A 2017 \"Law\" named for this scientist provided amnesty to UK men charged under anti-homosexuality legislation.TheBattleoftheAtlanticbegantippinginthe favor of the Allies in large part due to this man cracking the German naval Enigma code. A machine which can replicate any computer algorithm is named for, for ten points, which British computer scientist?",
      "answer": "AlanTuringor Alan MathisonTuring"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after\nit was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the\nVenetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points,\nname this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.",
        "answer": "compass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other great navigational problem was solved by John Harrison with the invention\nof the \"Sea Clock\" in 1730, winning a namesake twenty-thousand pound prize?",
        "answer": "longitude, determining a ship's longitude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\"\nform was pioneered by János Bolyai (pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai) and the Russian Nikolai\nLobachevsky (pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee). For 10 points, name this math field whose\nfoundational text is the Elements by Euclid (pr. YOOK-lid), which discusses the parallel\npostulate and Pythagorean theorem.",
        "answer": "geometry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other kind of mathematics was invented simultaneously by Gottfried Leibniz and\nIsaac Newton, who long quarreled over the credit for its discovery?",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Bahcall and Raymond Davis searched for these particles in the Homestake experiment.\nThe 1956 experiment of Clyde Cowan and Frederick Reines confirmed their existence. Enrico\nFermi coined the name for these particles, whose \"flavor oscillation\" was a problem of late\ntwentieth-century physics. For 10 points, name these particles with very little mass and no charge.",
        "answer": [
          "neutrinos",
          "antineutrinos",
          "solar neutrinos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The neutrino was first proposed, though without a name, by what scientist, whose\nconcept of particle spin led him to formulate a namesake \"exclusion principle\" about fermions?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Pauli",
          "Pauli"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Biologist George Gaylord Simpson was a vehement opponent of this theory. Frank Taylor first\nproposed this theory in 1908, based on observing similarities in distant mountain ranges. This\ntheory was picked up in 1912 by Alfred Wegener, who popularized it. For 10 points, identify this\ntheory, ancestral to plate tectonics, which states that large land masses move over time.",
        "answer": "continental drift"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wegener proposed that the continents could be fit together to form an \"Urkontinent,\" a\nprehistoric land mass now known by what Greek-derived name?",
        "answer": "Pangaea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jacob Bernoulli discovered that this number is the \"force of interest,\" the limit of the interest\naccruable on a dollar by increasing the frequency of compounding. A 1727 paper on the\nexplosive force of cannons introduced this number as the base of the natural logarithm. For 10\npoints, identify this mathematical constant named for its Swiss popularizer.",
        "answer": [
          "e",
          "Euler's number",
          "Euler's constant"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Euler (pr. OY-ler) also established graph theory in an attempt to solve the problem\ninvolving seven of what kind of structure in Königsberg?",
        "answer": [
          "bridges"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory was advocated by John Needham due to a faulty experimental design. Lazzaro\nSpallanzani argued against this theory by showing that Needham had failed to entirely seal the\nboiled flask used before observing “animalcules.” For 10 points, name this theory finally put to\nrest by Louis Pasteur, which holds that rotting food directly creates life.",
        "answer": "spontaneous generation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What scientist, the namesake of cells found around nerves, coined the dogma that “all\ncells come from pre-existing cells” following the collapse of spontaneous generation theory?",
        "answer": [
          "Theodor Schwann",
          "Schwann"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following the acceptance of this theory, Koch’s Postulates were developed. Girolamo Fracastoro was\nthe first to propose this theory, which Francesco Redi supported by observing 3 jars of meatloaf and eggs\nover time. The discrediting of spontaneous generation finally led to the widespread acceptance of this\ntheory. For ten points, Galen’s miasma theory was replaced by what theory that diseases are caused by\nmicroscopic organisms like viruses and bacteria?",
        "answer": [
          "germ theory of disease",
          "germ"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Spontaneous generation was disproven by this French microbiologist who also discovered that\nheating beer killed harmful bacteria.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis Pasteur",
          "Pasteur"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Isaac Barrow and served 33 years as Lucasian Professor of Mathematics in\nCambridge. His treatise Opticks introduced the corpuscular theory of light. This physicist laid the\nframework for classical mechanics in his three-volume Principia Mathematica, and he feuded with\nGottfried Leibniz over credit for the invention of calculus. For ten points, name this British physicist and\nmathematician who devised three laws of motion.",
        "answer": [
          "Sir Isaac Newton",
          "Newton"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In possible reference to the short stature of his rival, Robert Hooke, Newton claimed that if he\nhad “seen further,” it was by standing on this metaphorical concept.",
        "answer": "the shoulders of giants"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After one of these events, Harry Fielding Reid developed his elastic-rebound theory. In the 1930s,\ntwo Caltech scientists were inspired by the apparent magnitude scale of stars to develop a system for\nmeasuring these events. That scale has been replaced by the Moment Magnitude scale. The Mercalli\nintensity scale measures the destruction caused by these events. The Richter scale also measures, for ten\npoints, what seismic events that cause massive shaking of the ground?",
        "answer": "earthquakes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earthquake intensity scales are logarithmic, as is this standard scale for measuring the intensity\nof sound. This system’s unit is named for a Scottish inventor.",
        "answer": [
          "decibel system",
          "bel",
          "decibel scale"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist described the “chemistry of the imponderable” in a Nobel Prize lecture explaining the\nwork of Henri Becquerel. This scientist co-authored a study comparing tumor cell and healthy cell death\nrates when exposed to an element that this chemist isolated in 1910, four years after the death of her\nhusband Pierre. The first woman to win a Nobel Prize was, for ten points, what Polish-French physicist\nwho discovered radium while studying radioactive decay?",
        "answer": [
          "Marie Sklodowska Curie",
          "Marie Curie",
          "Marie Sklodowska",
          "Sklodowska",
          "Curie"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marie Curie isolated radium from a sample of radium chloride via a cathode of this element;\nthe radium reacted with this element to form an amalgam. This element, which is a liquid at room\ntemperature, has largely been phased out of use in scientific thermometers.",
        "answer": [
          "mercury",
          "Hg"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These devices, including some installed on Arizona’s Mount Bigelow, were improved after Cold War work on monitoring Soviet satellites inspired the development of adaptive optics. Karl Jansky names a series of 27 of these devices in New Mexico that form a Very Large Array. Isaac Newton invented a form of these devices with reduced aberration; that reflecting type improved on the refracting version, which Galileo used to observe the moons of Jupiter. For ten points, name these astronomical devices.",
        "answer": "telescopes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Very Large Array of telescopes detect signals in this region of the electromagnetic spectrum. This type of wave was first discovered coming from space by Karl Jansky in 1931 at Bell Labs.",
        "answer": "radio waves"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “transforming principle” of this molecule was discovered in an experiment on mice by Frederick Griffith. Evidence for this molecule’s purpose was found in a 1952 experiment using sulfur, phosphorous, and bacteriophages. X-ray diffraction pictures taken by Rosalind Franklin helped earn Watson and Crick a Nobel Prize for determining the double helix structure of, for ten points, what molecule that carries genetic instructions?",
        "answer": "DNA or deoxyribonucleic acid BONUS:ThesetwoAmericanscientistsperformedtheaforementioned1952experimentthatdemonstrated how DNA, not proteins, contained genetic material. ANSWER: Alfred Hershey and Martha Chase 2 The death of a ruler of this empire at the hands of Tamerlane led to an interregnum ended at the Battle of C¸amurlu. An Albanian revolt against this empire was led by a former general named Skanderbeg, and this empire defeated a Christian coalition at the Battle of Varna in 1444. Ibrahim the Mad and Murad the Great were sultans of, for ten points, what empire that, under Mehmed II, conquered Constantinople from the Byzantines in 1453? ANSWER: Ottoman Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ottoman Interregnum began with the death of this Ottoman sultan, called “the Thunderbolt,” and ended with Mehmed I’s aforementioned victory at C¸amurlu.",
        "answer": [
          "Bayezid I or Bayezid the Thunderbolt",
          "Bayezid Yildirim"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This US state was first formally claimed by Commodore John D. Sloat, who became its first military governor. After the city of Sonoma in this state was seized by the forces of William Ide and John C. Fremont, it briefly became its own republic. This site of the Bear Flag Revolt received a massive influx of settlers called “forty-niners” after a valuable commodity was discovered at Sutter’s Mill. For ten points, name this state that underwent a massive gold rush in 1848.",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This businessman arrived in California in 1853 to open a dry goods store, from which he marketed a new invention of one of his customers, riveted denim jeans.",
        "answer": "Levi Strauss"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man with this surname created photography’s first glass negative, which featured his father’s reflecting telescope. Another person with this surname embarked on a nighttime ride to deliver news that she discovered her eighth comet with the naked eye; that woman with this surname helped draft Catalogue of Nebulae and Clusters of Stars with her brother, whose Observatory House was equipped with a 40-foot telescope used in his discovery of two of Saturn’s moons. For ten points, name this surname, held by English astronomers Caroline and William, who discovered Uranus.",
        "answer": "Herschel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When William Herschel discovered Uranus in 1781, he initially named it after this English monarch.",
        "answer": "George III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Thisscientistnamesalawthatrelatestheproductoftwomasseswiththeinversesquareofthedistance separating them. This thinker’s essay General Scholium, which included the quotation “Hypotheses non fingo,” was an addendum to his Principia. Independent of Gottfried Leibniz, this scientist invented calculus. For ten points, name this scientist whose laws of inertia, acceleration, and action and reaction form the three laws of motion.",
        "answer": "Sir Isaac Newton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Isaac Newton’s work on the three laws of motion developed from this earlier scientist’s three laws of planetary motion.",
        "answer": "Johannes Kepler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure names an effect in which the rate of fermentation increases with low levels of oxygen. This figure, who is credited with disproving spontaneous generation, saved the life of Joseph Meister by administering an invention of his, the rabies vaccine. Antoine van Leeuwenhoek and this man are considered the fathers of microbiology. For ten points, name this French scientist who names a process where heat is applied to destroy germs in milk.",
        "answer": "Louis Pasteur"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis Pasteur also invented a vaccine for this bacterial infection caused by the spores of a species of Bacillus, which were sent in letters to politicians in a late 2001 terrorist attack.",
        "answer": "anthrax"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's vast selection of scientific works ranged from The Power of Movement in Plants to The Expression of the Emotions in Man and Animals. His best known theory was defended in 1860 by Thomas Henry Huxley, who was known as this man's \"bulldog.\" This man wrote about his theory of sexual selection in The Descent of Man. This man studied finches in the Galapagos while voyaging on the HMS Beagle. For ten points, name this English naturalist who authored On the Origin of the Species.",
        "answer": "Charles Darwin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The full title of On the Origin of Species includes the subtitle \"by means of\" this two word term, coined by Darwin and defined as the process by which species that are best able to adapt tend to survive and reproduce.",
        "answer": "Natural Selection"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Lorentz transformation was confirmed by tests of this theory, including the Ives-Stilwell Experiment and the Kennedy-Thorndike Experiment. This theory's development introduced terms into physics such as spacetime and time dilation and helped scientists predict gravitational waves and black holes. For ten points, give this shared name of two interrelated theories by Albert Einstein, divided into \"general\" and \"special\" types, that applies to all physical phenomena in the absence of gravity.",
        "answer": [
          "Relativity",
          "Special Relativity",
          "General Relativity"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though Einstein developed the theories of Relativity and several other groundbreaking discoveries, his 1921 citation for this major award only specifically mentioned his explanation of the Photoelectric Effect.",
        "answer": "Nobel Prize in Physics"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ITALIAN CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is home to the Colosseum?",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the supposed site of Galileo’s experiment dropping weights off the Leaning Tower?",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is situated on over one hundred islands, separated by canals?",
          "answer": "Venice"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the capital of Tuscany and the birthplace of the Renaissance?",
          "answer": "Florence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to La Scala Opera House and was ruled by the Visconti family?",
          "answer": "Milan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of Christopher Columbus?",
          "answer": "Genoa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the “fair” setting of Shakespeare’s Romeo and Juliet?",
          "answer": "Verona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to many of Palladio’s villas and an 800-year old university where Galileo taught math?",
          "answer": "Padua"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Italian city..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Manhattan Project",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Weapons that were developed by the Manhattan Project.",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons",
            "atomic bombs",
            "similar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German scientist who developed the theories of relativity and convinced FDR to start the Manhattan Project.",
          "answer": "Albert Einstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Material used by the Manhattan Project to power its weapons, supplemented by the more readily available plutonium.",
          "answer": "uranium"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of the weapon used to attack Hiroshima.",
          "answer": "Little Boy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last name of the husband and wife who were convicted of spying on the project for the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Julius and Ethel Rosenbergs"
        },
        {
          "question": "July 16, 1945 event in which “the Gadget” was tested, the first detonation of the Manhattan Project’s weaponry.",
          "answer": "Trinity test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scientist who headed the project and quoted the Bhagavad Gita while observing the aforementioned test.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "National lab in New Mexico where the project was headquartered.",
          "answer": "Los Alamos National Laboratory"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Inventions",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Invention whose patent caused a feud between Elisha Grey and Alexander Graham Bell.",
          "answer": "telephone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Navigation system based on a series of over 30 satellites that was developed by the US Air Force.",
          "answer": "GPS or Global Positioning System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ben Franklin invention that protected buildings from damage during storms.",
          "answer": "lightning rod"
        },
        {
          "question": "Household device made possible by an image dissector developed by Philo Farnsworth.",
          "answer": "television or TV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inventor of the mechanical reaper who established a manufacturing business in Chicago.",
          "answer": "Cyrus McCormick"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry that was greatly improved by Norbert Rillieux’s [rill-yoo’s] evaporator, which increased the concentration of cane juice.",
          "answer": [
            "sugar industry",
            "sugarcane"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Four-word phrase transmitted by Samuel Morse from Washington to Baltimore in 1844.",
          "answer": "What hath God wrought?"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proprietor of the Frying Pan Ranch who invented barbed wire.",
          "answer": "Joseph Glidden"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was the loser of the Battle of (20 pts) ",
        "Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped (10 pts) ",
        "cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Julius von Sachs identified the organelles in which this process takes place. The\nexperiments of Jan Ingenhousz (pr. ING-en-hoos) showed that this process altered the mass\nof the (20 pts) ",
        "organisms involved. Joseph Priestley performed an experiment involving a candle\nand (10 pts) ",
        "mint that showed that this process changes the composition of air. For 10 points, identify\nthis process of plants using light to create sugars from carbon dioxide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "photosynthesis",
        "Calvin cycle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This mathematician proved the undecidability of the halting problem. A finite set of user\ninstructions, an infinitely long memory tape, and a symbol reader make up a theoretical (20 pts) ",
        "machine conceived by this man; if a problem is computable, that device can solve\nit, according to a hypothesis named for this man and Alonzo Church. A computer that is\nindistinguishable from a human in (10 pts) ",
        "conversation would pass this man’s namesake test. For ten\npoints, name this British computer scientist who helped break the Enigma code during World War II\nbefore being prosecuted for his homosexuality."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alan Turing",
        "Turing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Cantilevers are used in the “atomic force” type of these devices, which were inspired by\na scanning, tunnelling type that won the 1986 Physics Nobel. Ernst Ruska and Max Knoll\nworked to develop types of these devices based on raster scattering of (20 pts) ",
        "electrons. In the\n17th century, Anton Van Leeuwenhoek built one of these devices to observe what he called\nanimalcules, organisms that Robert (10 pts) ",
        "Hooke later noted were made up of cells. For ten points,\nname these scientific tools that allow you to see very small things."
      ],
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A book about this concept in a Free Society was written by one of its critics, Paul Feyerabend. This concept’s “revolutionary” and “normal” phases were detailed in a 1962 book about the Structure of its (20 pts)",
        "Revolutions. Thomas Kuhn’s work on this subject introduced the term “paradigm shift” for momentous occasions in its history, such as (10 pts)",
        "Einstein’s theories of general relativity. For ten points, name this modern field of study divided into subfields such as biology, chemistry, and physics. ANSWER:science(acceptScienceinaFreeSociety;acceptTheStructure of Scientific Revolutions) (5) As Prime Minister, this man allowed journalists to be arrested for covering the “Ergenekon” trials. The Justice and Development Party was founded by this man, whose government was the target of a brief uprising by the (+) Peace at Home Council that they blamed on the Gu¨len movement, named for a Pennsylvania-based businessman named Fethullah Gu¨len. A July 2016 (*) coup d’etat in the streets of Ankara and Istanbul failed to oust, for ten points, what President of Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": "Recep Tayyip Erdogan , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was speculated to have been an act of sabotage by Hugo Eckener, a theory supported by the discovery of sulfur on a valve cap. Another hypothesis blames this event an electric shock strong enough to puncture (20 pts)",
        "fabric. This event, which occurred near the mooring station at the Naval Air Station in Lakehurst, (10 pts)",
        "New Jersey, was caused by the use of hydrogen gas. Herbert Morrison cried “oh, the humanity!” while reporting on, for ten points, what 1937 disaster in which an airship caught fire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Hindenburg disaster"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This mathematician proved that every Riemannian manifold can be embedded into some Euclidean space. This man, who once gave a presentation to the American Mathematical Society in which he claimed to have solved the Riemann hypothesis, was (20 pts)",
        "killed with his wife in a taxi accident after receiving the Abel prize in 2015. The 1994 Nobel for Economics was awarded to this man for his work in (10 pts)",
        "game theory, specifically the introduction of his namesake equilibrium. For ten points, name this mathematician whose struggle with schizophrenia was portrayed in the film A Beautiful Mind."
      ],
      "answer": "John Forbes Nash"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A laboratory with this name had scientists who demonstrated the wave nature of matter and created the transistor. A company founded by a man with this surname agreed to the Kingsbury Commitment with the government and later split into (20 pts)",
        "\"baby\" versions, like Verizon. A man with this surname called his assistant Thomas Watson to come to his room by using a device he invented. That Scottish man with this surname founded American (10 pts)",
        "Telephone and Telegraph. For ten points, the first practical telephone was invented by a man with what surname?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bell",
        "Alexander Graham Bell Page 9 of 10"
      ]
    }
  ]
}